

# Ashley C. Lowe Mackenzie

### ENVIRONMENTAL ECONOMIST

4969 MAUNALANI CIRCLE HONOLULU HAWAII 96816 5412706885 ALOWEMAC@HAWAII.EDU

#### **Objective**

I am an Environmental Economist with research interests at the intersection of social and ecological systems, in particular public lands, natural resources, and outdoor recreation. My work leverages empirical frameworks within environmental economics, notably non-market valuation, benefit-cost analysis, and causal inferences. I've examined emerging public land management questions involving visitation and social media, public health advisories impact on the economic value of recreation and the prioritization of adaptation strategies to improve community resilience given challenges from sea level rise and ocean acidification.

_	-				
P۸	ci	ti	n	n	C

2024-Present Assistant Professor (I3) Non-Tenure

University of Hawaii at Manoa

Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Management

2023 **Post Doctorate Fellow** 

University of Hawaii at Manoa

Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Management

Kirsten Oleson ~ Oleson Lab

**Education** 

2018-2023 **Oregon State University** 

Ph.D. Applied Economics

Dissertation: "Understanding the New Outdoor Recreation Paradigm in the  $\,$ 

Era of Social Media and Increasing Public Health Advisories"

Link to dissertation

2017-2020 **Oregon State University** 

**MS Applied Economics** 

Thesis: "Is Instagram Influencing Visitation to Public Lands?"

Advisor: Steven Dundas

2008-2011 **Portland State University** 

**BS Economic** 

Research Experience

2023 Postdoctoral Fellow at University of Hawaii Manoa

This project is funded through NOAA Ocean Acidification Project. I am translating outputs of an ecological model into outcomes for Hawaii's people through the ecosystem provision of recreation and tourism. The focus is on identify spatial vulnerabilities across the island to improve

community resilience.



The dataset of this project is exploring secondary data developed from the lab, reservation systems from DLNR and data from Department of Tourism Hawaii.

Work Schedule: 40hrs/week Supervisors: Kristen Oleson

#### 2021-2022 Graduate Research Assistant at OSU

This project was funded by the Oregon Department of Transportation examining the potential impacts from highway infrastructure failures stemming from coastal erosion and sea level rise. For this analysis I used Oregon state park reservation data sets and visitor levels to public parks to estimate various potential impacts of adaptation strategies, including permanent beach width loss from coastal hardening, benefits and cost associated with access to amenity, as well as cost from added emissions from reroutes using the social cost of carbon.

The analysis uses both market and non-market values in a benefit cost analysis addressing. natural resource connections, community resilience through land-use planning, climate change vulnerability and adaptation. Collaborates with managers, policymakers, and scientists to produce research addressing the needs of natural resource managers, policymakers, and communities.

Work Schedule: 20hrs/week Supervisors: Steven Dundas Phone: (541) 737-1402

#### Summer 2019 Data Analyst at Oregon State Parks and Recreational Dept (OPRD)

Conducted field work on visitation to Oregon State Parks validating estimation methods for OPRD. I collected visitor counts and compared it to car counters at entrances of day use area. We also examined other visitator counting systems such as trail counters and newer traffic counter monitoring systems.

Disseminates research results to peers and park managers.

Work Schedule: 40hrs/week Supervisors: Caleb Dickson Phone: 503-428-8790

### Teaching Experience

#### 2024 University of Hawai'i at Māona Professor

Department of Natural Resource and Environmental Management

- UPCOMING: NREM 691 Valuing Nature Fall 2024
- UPCOMING: NREM 429 Spreadsheet Modeling for Business and Economic Analysis Fall 2024
- NREM 494 Environmental Problem Solving Capstone On-campus

Course using strutured decision making and applying it to a local environmental problem.

#### 2023 Western Oregon University Instructor

Department of Sustainability



• SUS 390 Global Climate Change On-campus

Course covering climate science using IPCC AR6, adaptation & mitigation strategies, historical climate policies, carbon wealth inequalities, economics, Social Cost of Carbon and carbon pricing.

Developed lectures, quizzes, exams, and homework

• SUS 340 Sustainability & Capitalism Ecampus
Currently designing course covering pillars of sustainability & capitalism
framework. I use UN Sustainability Development Goals to examine the
how the pillars and incentives of capitalism fit within the framework.

Developed lectures, quizzes, exams, and homework

## 2020 **Oregon State University Instructor**

Department of Applied Economics

• AEC 253 Environmental Law, Policy and Economics Ecampus

#### 2018-2021 Oregon State University Teaching Assistant

Applied Economic and Sustainability Departments

- AEC 253 Environmental Law, Policy and Economics Ecampus
- AEC 525 Applied Econometrics
  - Graduate level lab teaching econometric commands in STATA
- AEC 447 Agriculture Price and Market Analysis
- AEC/ECON 432 Environmental Law Ecampus & On-campus
- AEC 388 Agricultural Law Ecampus & On-campus
- AEC/ECON 352 Environmental Economics and Policy
- SUS 350 Sustainability Communities (3quarters) Ecampus
  - Including a role in developing a new canvas course material on Canvas.
- SUS 304 Sustainability Assessment (3quarters) Ecampus
- AEC 253 Environmental Law, Policy and Economics (3quarters)
   Ecampus & On-campus
  - In-class conducting Pollution Control Games, highlighting the difference between command and control, taxes, and Cap & Trade.
- AEC 122 Introduction to Climate Change Economics and Policy Ecampus & On-campus

#### **Publications**

#### 2023 **Publications**

Olsen, M. J., J Allan, S. J. Dundas, A. Lowe Mackenzie, M. Krivova, A. Senogles, B. A. Leshchinsky, J. Hermann, and C. Parrish (2024). US Highway 101 Coastal Hazard Vulnerability and Assessment for Mitigation Prioritization, Oregon Department of Transportation Project, Federal Highway Administration, Final Report

Lowe Mackenzie, A., S. J. Dundas, and B. Zhao. (2024) *The Instagram Effect: Is Social Media Influencing Visitation to Public Land?* Land Economics. DOI: https://doi.org/10.3368/le.100.2.122920-0192R1



2022 Working Paper

Lowe Mackenzie, A., S.J. Dundas. Is a Photo Worth 1,000 Likes? The Influence of Instagram at National Parks *Link* 

Lowe Mackenzie, A., A. Dugstad & K. Oleson. The economic value of forest campsite closures in Hawai'i

Lowe Mackenzie, A., S.J. Dundas & Dickson C. The Effects of Public Health Advisories on the Value of Recreational Camping

Current Work in Progress

Integrating spatial dynamics and recreational values from the impacts of ocean acidification on coral reefs to the Hawaiian Islands

Estimating the Impacts of Removing Oregon's Severance Tax on Large Industrial Timber Harvesting

Fourthcoming WEAI Summer Conference - Seattle, WA

Accepted MSEAS – Japan

AERE Summer Conference - DC, USA

**Presentations** 

2023 **Camp Resources** 

Is a Photo Worth 1,000 Likes? Visitation Modeling and Influence of

Instagram at National Parks Aug. 8 2023

2020 **People and Nature At OSU** 

Is Instagram Influencing Visitation to Public Lands?

Professional training

2022 Graduate Teaching Seminar Oregon State University

Description: focuses on evidence-based pedagogical practices with an emphasis on practical strategies and problem-solving, and will be tuned to graduate students' needs and the classes they are instructing.

2019 Training Social Justice Education Initiative Workshop

Description: Apply a vocabulary of basic terms in common with other participants. Recognize how history relates to the current context of Oregon and OSU. Describe some of your own social identities. Recognize that your OSU community is comprised of diverse and intersecting social identities. Understand that a dominant culture

exists, even if it is invisible to you.

**Computer skills** Programming Python, R, HTML, markdown, JavaScript, CSS

Applications Visual Studio Code, QGIS, Rstudio, Latex, Anaconda, Stata,

ArcGis, Final Cut, Matlab, Git, Github, Google Cloud



Libraries • File Directories : macOS, Microsoft Windows, Ubuntu/Unix

• JavaScript: D3.js, C3.js, bootstrap, Leaflet, JQuery, dc.js

• R: tidyverse, NLP, dplyr, tidyr, ggplot2, tidytext

• Python: pandas, pip, NumPy, Matplotlib, NLK, spaCy

References

<u>Dr. Steven</u> Department of Applied Economics – Oregon State University Phone:

<u>Dundas</u> (541) 737-1402

\*Advisor Chair & CoAuthor

<u>Dr. Ashley</u> Department of Forest Ecosystems & Society – Oregon State University

<u>D'Antonio</u> Phone: (541) 737-5043 *Committee* • Committee Member

• Advisor for recreation ecology concentration

<u>Dr. Nadia A.</u> Department of Applied Economics – Oregon State University Phone:

<u>Streletskaya</u> (347) 735.1787

Committee • Advisor for behavioral economics concentration

<u>Dr. Kirsten</u> Dept. of Natural Resources & Environmental Management – University

Oleson of Hawaii at Manoa Phone: (808)956.8864

Post Doc PI Post Doc PI on Ocean Acidification